Charles P. Sonett Papers, 1962-2010 (bulk 1973-1997)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Charles P. Sonett Papers 1962-2010 (bulk 1972-19997)
MS 520
Sonett, Charles P.
The Charles Sonett papers is comprised of the personal and professional papers of nuclear physicist Charles P. Sonett. The bulk of the material relates to his career as an astronomical researcher and administrator at the Department of Planetary Sciences and the Lunar Planetary Laboratory, University of Arizona.
2.5 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Biographical Note
Charles P. Sonett was born on January 15, 1924 in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, of Hungarian parents. When he was a young boy his family moved to Trona California, forty miles southwest of Death Valley. He attended Los Angeles High School and became a member of the LA Amateur Astronomical Society.
Following high school, Sonett attended UCLA and majored in physics. After 2 years of college and the bombing of Pearl Harbor he enlisted in the Army where he was assigned to the 103rd Infantry Division. On March 13, 1945 Sonett stepped on a German mine while on patrol in France, his injuries led to the battlefield amputation of his left leg.
He returned to UCLA in 1946 to continue his undergraduate degree in physics. Sonett ultimately transferred to UC Berkley where he graduated in 1948. In June of that same year he married Virginia Louise Hooten, also a graduate of UC Berkley.
His first job was with the Naval Radiological Defense Laboratory at Hunters Point in San Francisco working on satellite planning. After only one year he returned to UCLA and received his masters of arts in 1951 and his doctorate in Nuclear Physics in 1954.
From 1954 through 1960 Dr. Sonett was employed by Ramo-Wooldridge Corporation in the Space Technology Laboratories. He was subsequently employed at NASA Headquarters, as Chief of Sciences, in the Lunar and Planetary Programs from 1960-1962. In 1962 Sonett was chosen as the head of the Space Sciences Division at NASA Ames Research Center, Moffett Field, California. Dr. Sonett remained at Ames Research Center for 11 years. Where he was a pioneer in space exploration and involved in the Pioneer Program, 1958-1969; Explorer Program, 1959-1976; Apollo Program, 1969-1972.
In 1969 he was awarded the NASA Exceptional Scientific Achievement Medal for significant scientific contribution toward achievement of aeronautical or space exploration goals.
Dr. Sonett was personally selected by Dr. Gerard P. Kuiper to replace him in 1973, as the director of the Lunar Planetary Laboratory (LPL) and the head of the Department of Planetary Science. During his tenure as director, 1973-1977, Sonett built and expanded an internationally recognized research and education program in solar system sciences at the University of Arizona.
Following his resignation as director, Sonett continued to be active in both research and teaching at the Lunar Planetary Laboratory and the Department of Planetary Sciences. In 1990 Dr. Sonett was involved in the Ulysses Program, a joint venture between The European Space Agency (ESA) and NASA. This mission was the first survey of the Sun's environment in space from its equator to the poles and over a wide range of solar activity conditions.
In 1992 the University of Arizona named Dr. Sonett a Regents’ Professor, the top title for university professors in the state. In 2003 he retired from teaching and research at the university as a Regents’ Professor Emeritus.
On April 30, 2004 the University of Arizona dedicated the Dr. Charles P. Sonett Space Science Building at 1541 E. University Blvd., Tucson, AZ. The building now houses approximately 45 scientists and support staff.
Charles P. Sonett died on September 30, 2011 at the age of 87.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 5 series
Series I: Personal Files, 1971-2010
Series II: Correspondence, 1962-1996,
Series III: Research, 1962-1996
Series IV: Publication/Presentations, 1955-1997
Series V: Subject files, 1972-2000
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of the personal and some professional papers of Charles P. Sonett. The bulk of the material consists of his correspondence with other noted astronomers and scientists, during his time at the Lunar Planetary Laboratory and the Department of Planetary Sciences. Other items in the collection are research files, publications/presentation, and subject files.
Gerard Peter Kuiper Papers, MS 480; Michael J. Drake Papers, MS 511.
Access Terms
Kuiper, Gerard,1905-1973
Sonett, Charles P.
United States. National Aeronautics and Space Administration--History.
University of Arizona--Department of Planetary Science--History.
University of Arizona--Lunar Planetary Laboratory--History.
Varves.
Moon--Origin.
Solar System--Age.
Magnetic fields.
Climate changes.
Solar Wind--research.
Tree-rings--research.
Aeronautics--Research--United States--History.
Sun--Observations.
Container List
- Series I: Personal files 1971-2010
  - Personal (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Correspondence 1962-1996
  Organized alphabetically by correspondent, includes both incoming and outgoing mail.
  - A, 1969-1993 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics (AIAA), )1972-1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Geophysical Union (AGU), 1980-1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - B, 1969-1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - C, 1969-1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - D, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - E, 1969-1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - F, 1969-1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - G, 1971-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Gault, Donald E., 1972-1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - H, 1969-1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - I, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - J, 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - K, 1969-1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - L, 1971-1994 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - M, 1972-1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Michaelis, Anthony, 1975-1994 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - N, 1970-1991 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - NASA, 1962-1988 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - O, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - P, 1971-1983 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - R, 1972-1989 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Runcorn, S.K., 1972-1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - S, 1965-1994 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Sagan, Carl, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Schubert, G., 1969-1975 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Suess, Hans E., 1981-1989 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - T, 1969-1988 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - U, 1968-1985 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - V, 1971-1989 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Vanyan, L.L., 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - W, 1967-1997 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Unknown, 1978-1993 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Series III: Reasearh Files 1962-1996
  Arranged alphabetically by title
  - Explorer 33 - 35 (notes, figures, programs), circa 1962-1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Explorer 33/35, 4-Way, Ames/Goddard (Project Close Encounters), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Explorer (Old Spectral Analyses), circa 1966 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Explorer Tape Programs – note on changes, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Houston original Plots “Velumes”, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Impact photographs/frames, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Impact Experiment notebook (Nova camera), 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Impact Experiment photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Pioneer B-Vector sphere plots, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Powers/Sigmas, circa 1971, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Tree-Ring research, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Tree-Ring research, circa 1982-1987 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Varve Mean Cycles notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Weeli Wooli Scans / Notes, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous (charts, figures, graphs, etc.), 1969-1996 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Series IV: Publications/Presentations 1955-1997, Organized chronologincally.
  - Sonett’s Publication list, 1955-1997 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Articles/presentations by Sonett, 1974-1994 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Transparencies for the Spring AGU meeting, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Elatina (figures, photographs, transparencies), circa 1980’s (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Figures not needed for Planetary Meeting presentation, circa 1980’s (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - TTau stars and the early heating of protoplanets, December 2, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Ulysses mission plasma data transparencies, circa1990’s (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - US-USSR Symposium on the influence of solar activity on climate, November 16-20, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Outline for a Lunar Physics book, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Lunar Plumes, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Series V: Subject Files 1972-2000
  - Two Proposals with Sonett’s involvement, 1972, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Manuscripts reviewed by Charles Sonett, 1975-2000 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Bibliography?, 1977-1980 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Photographs of Varves, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Note: Varve is an annual layer of sedimentary material deposited in lakes and fiords by glacial melt waters, consisting of two distinct bands of sediment deposited in summer and winter. Some of the photographs were taken at Port Askaig, Scotland.
  - Unknown rock, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)